My name is Yaroslav Halchenko and I am talking to you from Dartmouth about DataLad project.
This project was initiated by me and Michael Hanke from Germany
and we had successful few years of collaboration. Before that you might know about us
because of our other projects such as PyMVPA and NeuroDebian.
I hope that you use them and they help you in your research projects.
More about these and other projects
You could discover if you go to the centerforopenneuroscience.org website, or you could also find
contacts for us in social media and before I proceed with the talk
I want first of all acknowledge work of others and the project. It wasn't only my and Michael's work
Our project is heavily based on Git-annex tool, which Joey Hess wrote for managing his own collection of files
which has nothing to do with science.
Also, he is well known for his work in Debian project
We had, we still have tireless workers on a project
Benjamin
working with Michael and Alex. Alex recently refurbished or wrote from scratch a new version of the website
I hope that you'll like it and we'll see a bit more of it later.
Also, we had Jason, Debanjum and Gergana working on the project.
They were quite successful to accomplish a lot within short period of time
So if you're looking for a project to contribute to it might be the interesting project for you to start
working on open source projects and leave in kind of your foot step in the
ecosystem of Open Source for Neuroscience.
This project is supported by NSF and
Federal Finistry for Education and Research in Germany.
If you go to centerforopenneuroscience.org you could discover more
interesting and exciting projects we either collaborate with it or contribute to.
Before we proceed I want actually to formulate the problem we are trying to solve DataLad.
Data is second class citizen within software platforms. What could that potentially be?
One of the aspects is if you look how people distribute data nowadays
Quite often you find that even large arrays of data are distributed in tarballs or zip files.
Problems were multiple with these ways of distribution if one file changes you need to re-distribute
Entire tarball which might be gigabytes in size, and that's why partially we also couldn't just adopt
technologies which are
Proven to work for software, let's say in Debian we distribute complete packages.
But again the problem is the same.
As long as you force
wrapping all the data together in some big file - it wouldn't work. It won't scale.
Also another problem is absent version of data.
And many people actually underappreciate it and think that it doesn't actually exist
or relates to their way of work. But no, actually this problem is quite generic.
So if you look into this
PhD comics caricature, you'll find that these probably relates to many
ways how you deal with files, data or
documents. And you could see that actually
how we tend to version our data is by providing - quite often - the date, right, which creates some kind of linear progression.
Right, so we annotate that: "Oh!"
"I've worked on these in those dates, but also maybe a little bit later..."
And we try to annotate it with some description of what was maybe done to the data
Right, so in this case. It was a test run
Then we test it again and calibrate it and then we ran into a problem, right? So...
All these, kind of, you saved the result of your work and annotated so later on you could
either get back to the previous state. Let's say maybe you indeed made an error and you want to rollback.
Or maybe you want to just compare what have you done, which broke your code or data?
Right, and as you could see those messages could be quite descriptive.
But the problem is that version control systems which are created for code are inadequate for data, right? So the problem is,
quite often, that it's duplication you have copy of the data in the version control system inside somewhere
so you couldn't use it directly.
But also it's present on your hard drive, so at least you have two copies quite often.
Or maybe it's duplicated and just on a single server, right?
I could give you examples were data in a version control system filled up the version control system and
meanwhile filling up the hard drive and
sometimes you try to commit new file and apparently ran out of space on the server and it might ruin your
version control back and then on the server
Rendering it impossible to get to the previous version, so you don't want to have that, right?
Then another problem is that there are no generic data distributions or at least there were no before DataLad.
So there is no efficient ways to
install and upgrade data sets and
When you also deal with different data hosting portals you need to learn how to navigate them
All right
you need to learn how you
authenticate, which page you need to go to and what to download and how to download it?
So just to get to that data set. And then, maybe you
get the announcement that dataset was fixed
and you need to repeat this over and over again trying to remember how to deal with it. And I'm not talking even if
the website became much better and sleeker and changed all the ways how it actually deals with downloads from what it did before.
Another aspect that data is rarely tested
So what does it mean for data to have bugs?
Any derived data is a product of running a script or some kind of procedure on
original data and generating new derived data.
Quite permanent ones which you could find in references later on in this presentation
is atlases. So Atlas is usually produced from the data writing some really sophisticated script
which generates new data:
the atlas. And those atlases could be buggy.
So how do you test the data? The same way as software. If we could establish this efficient process where we
produce some data and verify that at least data meets the assumptions
which you expect. If it's population or probability in the area
which must be present in the entirety of population,
then operability should be up to 100 or nearby 100. If it doesn't add up,
then you have a bug. It's really simple assumption
But very verifying that your data doesn't have...
Doesn't break those is really important.
Unified way how we deal with data, and the code could help to establish those data testing procedures.
Also, it's quite difficult to share your derived data. If downloaded some data set from an well known portal...
How do you share it? What data could be shared?
Where do you deposit it so people later on
Could download maybe original data, and your derive data without even worrying that oh
They need to get this piece from an original source and your derived data from another place
So how do we link those pieces together to make it convenient?
What we're trying to achieve is to make managing of the data as easy as managing code and software.
Is it possible? I hope that you'll see that it is so
What DataLad is based on...
Is in two pieces and one of them is Git. I hope that everybody knows what Git is.
But I'll give small presentation nevertheless. So Git is a version control system
and initially it was developed to manage Linux project code, if somebody doesn't know what Linux is this is one of the
most recognized and probably mostly used, because it's used everywhere: on the phones, on the servers, on the operating systems.
It's free and open source and it's developed into open and at some point they needed new version control system
Which would scale for the demand of having lots of code managed there and many people working with it
So it's not a geeky project just for... Between a few people.
It is developed by hundreds.
It's used by millions.
What's great about Git is that it's distributed.
So content is available across all copies of the repository if you clone the repository
You have the entire history of the project
and you could get to any point in that development you could compare different versions.
You could do exactly the same things as original developers dated on this repository.
So it provides you as much flexibility to accomplish things locally
without requiring any network access.
Git became a backbone for github and other social coding portals.
So github came to fill the niche that there were no convenient online resource
where people could easily share these repositories and work on them together.
So git is just a tool and github is just a web portal which provides you
a convenient centralized management of the repositories and collaboration between people.
But it's not a single one there are other
systems which use Git underneath.
Gitlab, Bitbucket, so...
It just creates this the entire ecosystem of the tool and additional services and resources.
What git is great for is very efficient management of textual information, right, so if you manage code, text, configuration files...
Maybe dumped some documentation or JSON files? So, all of those were nicely managed by git because it has really good mechanism to
annotate the differences and compress that efficiently.
So all those distributed copies are actually not that big.
But the problem or inefficiency of Git
is this exactly distributed nature of it. That it stores all the copies of the documents
on all the systems, right? So, if I have big files, then it becomes inefficient.
because now you will have two copies, right? You will have one on the hard drive (at least two copies)...
One on your hard drive and then one committed into Git.
Then if you push this into Github you will have again a
big copy of that file somewhere and anybody who clones that repository
might wait for a while to just get it and then
they might be a little bit upset because they wanted just one file from the repository and didn't care to download a gigabyte
of data just to see it.
So it's inefficient for storing data.
What is the other tool we rely on, as I said, written by Joey Hess it's Git-annex.
So the idea was to build on top of git to provide management for the data files
Without committing those files directly into Git.
So git-annex allows you to add data files under Git control without
committing the content of the files into Git.
While playing with Git-annex and DataLad you might see that files get replaced with the same link.
So what git-annex commits into Git is actually just symlink
which points to the file which contains the data.
This way you can commit really lightweight symlink and keep the data on the hard drive and a single
copy. Sorry, it's not in Git. And then what git-annex does, it orchestrate the
management of those files between
Different clones of the repository or so called other way special nodes.
But also it provides access to those files if they are let's say uploaded on to some website,
so you have a URL. You could associate the URL with the file, you could upload it to FTP,
you could upload it to web server.
You could even get content through BitTorrent, or you could use Amazon s3 storage as your
container for the files and it allows for custom extensions.
Let's say you could upload data to Dropbox, Google Drive, box.com and many, many other
data hosting provider.
Git-annex takes care also about avoiding the limitations of those platforms.
Let's say box.com from public account, it doesn't allow you to have files larger than I believe hundred megabytes.
Git-annex will chop it up so on the box.com you'll have little pieces
You will not use them directly from box.com, but then git-annex
will re-assemble the big file when it gets it onto your hard drive so all those
Conveniences and in addition encryption, that's if you want to share some sensitive data, and you cannot just upload it
Unencrypted to the public service all those are provided by git-annex.
Also additional feature which we don't use in a project is git-annex assistant which is Dropbox like
Synchronization mechanism you could establish
synchronization between your Git, git-annex repositories across multiple servers and
configure them really flexibly so you have that's a backup of on off all the data files on one server and
Some other server will have only files which it cares about let's say
Data files another one might have only video files
another one may be just music files who knows so flexibility is there and
It's all up to you to configure what you want where.
In our project we don't use it yet, but we do use it locally for synchronizing
different git-annex repositories.
But another problem here, so we have really
Great two tools Git and git-annex, but both of them work on a single repository level.
So, the work in a git repository you need to go into that directory and
Accomplish whatever you want to do. It kind of doesn't go along well with the notion of distribution
You don't care where you are you just want to, on your hard drive, so you just want to say:
Oh, search, find me something, install this and
give me access to this data. Right? Or get me give me this file
Even though maybe I'm not in that git or git-annex repository
Also another kind of aspect those are just tools so similarly like
how GitHub provided convenient portal to the tool git.
We want to accomplish something where we use these tools which are agnostic of domain of the data
(let's say neuroimaging) to give you guys access to those terabytes of publicly shared data already
Which lives out there somewhere, so we don't need to collect it. We don't need to
make copy of it locally, right, it's already there, so
What we want to achieve is just to provide access to that data without
Mirroring it on our servers or without duplicating it elsewhere
Before going into demos I want to give you kind of more illustrative demo of what is data lifecycle here of data
which we provide by DataLad.
Let's imagine that we have a data set which comes initially from OpenfMRI, right, and live somewhere in the cloud or
On data hosting portal actually we have two copies of the data one of them might be in the tarball, somewhere on HTTP server
right and another one might be
Extracted from the tarball, somewhere on a cloud which might have HTTP access might have S3 access,
but the point is that data is there and
Then we have a data user and that's us right me you everybody who wants to use this data
So now options are: we either...
Go down on the tarball extract it or we learn how to use S3 and go and install some tool
Browse S3 bucket, download those files.
But what we are trying to establish here is actually a middle layer, right?
We want to provide data distribution which might be hosted somewhere, maybe it's on github maybe in our server
Where I'll take this data available online and will automatically crawl it so here
I mentioned this command crawl which is one of the commands DataLad provides to automate monitoring of external resources
So we could get them into Git repositories and actually you could see here that these
Greenish-yellow
Why you don't draw here? Greenish yellow...
color.
Why you don't draw here?
Here we go! So, this greenish yellow color represents just a Content reference
Instead of the actual content, that's why we could host it on github or anywhere because it doesn't have the actual data
So we collect those data sets into collections, which we might share
let's save the one which we share from data sets that are on DataLad.org
underneath we use git modules which is built-in mechanism within Git to organize these collections of
multiple repositories while keeping track of burgeoning information
So you could get the entire collection of let's say of OpenfMRI data sets
For a specific date for a specific version if you want to reproduce some of these else analysis
And then we are making it possible to install
Arbitrary number of those data sets we are unified interface
So here we mentioned command datalad --install which you will see later and hopefully
Those parameters like install into current data set and get all the data
Will it be less surprising and also we provide shortcuts so which I'll talk about later
But the point is that you could now easily
Install those data sets onto your local hard drive, and if you are doing some processing
It might add results of the process in this case. We've got new file filtered bold file, which we could easily add
Into this repository and which means which is committed into the repository
Under git-annex control. And later we could publish this entirety of maybe collection of the datasets
to multiple places one of them might be github or we publish only the
repository itself without actually data files again
Those are just symlinks and maybe offload the actual data to some server which my HTTP server
or some other server through some mechanism right, but the point is that data goes somewhere and the magic happens here
Thanks to the git-annex because that's the Beast which keeps track of were each data file
Could be obtained from so this red links point to the information
What git-annex stores for us that I let's say this bald file is available from original web portal right it's available from S3 bucket,
it might be coming from a tarball, so that's one of the extensions
we added to git-annex to support extraction of the files from the tarball.
So it becomes really transparent to the user and this new file
We published it there. So it might be available now through HTTP so people who cloned this repository
Would be able to get any file from original storage or from any derived data
Which we published on our website?
So that's kind of the main idea behind DataLad.
So, altogether
DataLad allows you to manage multiple repositories organized into these super datasets
Which are just collection of git repositories using standard git sub-modules mechanism.
It supports both git and ggit-annex repository, so if you have
Just regular git repositories where you don't want to add any data. It's perfectly fine.
We can crawl external online data resources and update git-annex repositories upon changes.
It seems to scale quite nicely because data stays with original data provider
so we don't need to increase the storage in our server and
We could use maybe or you could use because anybody could use DataLad to publish
their collections of the datasets on
github and maybe offloading data itself to portals like box.com or dropbox.
What happens now that we have unified access to data regardless of its origin
I didn't care if data comes from openfMRI or CRCNS.
The only difference might be that you need to authenticate it. Let's say CRCNS doesn't allow download without authentication.
So DataLad will ask you for credentials, which you should store locally in the hard drive
Nothing is shared with us and later on when you need to get more data
Just to use those credentials to authenticate in your behalf to CRCNS,
download those tarballs extract it for you, so you didn't need to worry about that and
Also, we take care about serialization, so if original website distributes only tarballs
We download tarballs for you, extract them and again
You didn't need to worry how the data is actually serialized by original data provider
What we do on top is that we aggregate metadata.
What metadata is? It is data about the data.
So let's say you have a data set which contains the data the results information about what this data
Set is about what it's named. What was its offer authors?
What might be the license if it's applicable?
so any additional information about the data constitutes metadata.
What we do in DataLad, we aggregate metadata, which we find about the original data sets and
Provide you convenient interface
So you could search across all of it across all the data sets which we already
Integrated in DataLad. And I hope you'll see the demonstration
quite appealing later on.
Then DataLad after you consumed added extended data sets or just created from scratch
You could share original or derived datasets publicly as I mentioned or internally you could always
publish them locally at your SSH may be to collaborate with somebody and that's what we do regularly and
Meanwhile we'll keep data
we could keep data available elsewhere, or you could even share the data set without sharing the data, which is quite keen as
Demonstration of good intent when you are about to publish the paper, that's what we did them with our recent submission
We publish the data set but not with the entirety of the data set
But just with first subject so reviewers could verify that there is
Good quality data
that
They could get access to it right and that the entirety of data is in principle available
And it was processed accordingly because the whole the entire Git history
is maintained and shared, but the data files are not
Okay and the additional benefit some of it, which is work in progress
You could export the data set if you want to share just the data itself you could
Export the data set and current version in a tarball and give it to somebody but more exciting feature
and we've been working on is exporting in to
some
Metadata heavy data formats if you're publishing scientific data
You will be asked to fill out a big spreadsheet, which is called easy to have
To annotate metadata for your data set it's really tedious and unpleasant job
But the beauty is that all that information is contained within
metadata of either data set or of git-annex. So we could automatically
export majority of information for you, so you just need to fill out left out information and be done
DataLad comes with both common line and Python interfaces
So you could work with it interactively either in common line or script it in bash or working with it interactively in the ipython
and script it with Python language it gives you the same capabilities and really similar syntax
Our distribution
Grew up already to cover over ten terabytes of data
We cover such data sets as OpenfMRI, CRCNS,
functional connectome
INDI data sets and even some data sets from Kaggle and some RatHole radio podcast show
Because it was a cool experiment to be able to crawl that website and collect all the data
About timing of the songs. So check it out
It's available on github although data stays as again with original provider
What is coming? More data, so we'll cover human connectome project and data available from x net servers
We want to provide extended metadata support, so we cover not only data sets
level data
But also data for separate files if you know about any other interesting data set or data provider
File a new issue, or shoot us an email.
we are also working on integrating with NeuroDebian, so you could apt-get install those datasets and the position of data to
OSF and in other platforms. Another interesting integration
Which we've done was to introduce DataLad support into HeuDiConv which stands for Heuristic DICOM Conversion Tool.
which allows you to
automate conversion of your DICOM data obtained from MRI scanner into NIfTI files
but we went one step further and
Standardized it to convert not only to DataLad data set but DataLad BIDS data sets.
Set so if you don't know what BIDS is, it is something you must know nowadays.
If you doing imaging research. It's brain imaging data structure format
Which describes how you should lay out your files on a file system so anybody who finds your data set will be immediately
capable to understand
your design how many subjects you have so it's standardized is beyond NIfTI. It standardized is how you
Work with your files so now
With this integration HeuDiConv we can obtain DataLad datasets
with BIDS if I'd neuroimaging data, so it's ready to be shared
It's ready to be processed by any BIDS compatible tool, so it opens ample
opportunities
And at this point I guess we should switch and do some demos
And before I actually give any demo I want to familiarize you with our new website DataLad.org
On top you could see
navigation for among major portions the website
One of them is about page
Just describes the purpose of the DataLad and provides
information about funding agencies and involved institutions
Next link is "Get DataLad"
Which describes how to install the DataLad. The easiest installation is if you are using your Debian already.
Then it just apt-get install DataLad command or you could find it in package manager and install it within second
Alternatively, if you are on OS-X or any other operating system. Windows support is initial but it
Should work in the basic set of features
you have to install git-annex by
going to git-annex website and
Into install page
choosing the operating system of your choice and following the instructions there how to get it and
after you installed git-annex
You just need to install DataLad from Python package index through pip-install datalad command.
Next page is features page
Which is actually led to by those pretty boxes on the main page and this page will go through
later in greater detail
Another interesting page is Datasets which presents you our
ultimate official distribution which points to datasets.datalad.org
which is the collection of data sets which already pre crawled for you and
That were we provide those data sets like for Open fRI
CRCNS
ADHD and
many others
I will just briefly describe the features of these
Basic website and mention that the such websites if you have any HTTP server available somewhere
Maybe institution provides because you will not host the data actually here, or you don't have to
you could upload similar views of your data sets pretty much anywhere where you could host a website and
OpenfMRI, let's say we go to OpenfMRI, it lists all those data sets
which we crawled from OpenfMRI, you could see also immediately mentioning of the version
here and version goes
from
What version OpenfMRI gave it but also with additional indices pointing to exact commits
Within our git repository I didn't find that version another neat feature here is
immediate
Search so you could start typing and now if you're interested in resting-state
So here we go it goes
Pretty fast and limits the view only the data sets where metadata
Mentions this word and say let's look for Haxby... There we go!
Or let's look for "movie". There we go! So, you could quickly identify the data sets by
browsing and we'll see how we could do
such actions later in the command line and
When you get to the data set of interest or it could be at any pretty much level you'll see on top the command which
Could be used to install this data set and described in some options
Let's say -r is to install this data set with any possible sub data set recursively.
There's -g to install it and also obtain all the data for it, and if you want to speed up the
obtaining the data you could use -J
And specify the number of parallel downloads your server and bandwidth could allow you
Okay, let's go back to DataLad website and another
Page on the website is development. So, if you're interested to help and contribute datasets provide
patches improve documentation
All of the development this is made in open. We use github intensively, we use Travis, we use codecov.
We use Grid for documentation so and that will be our next point
Documentation is hosted on docs.datalad.org and it provides
Not yet as thorough documentation as we wanted but some
documentation about major features of the dataset or a comparison between Git, git-annex and DataLad.
But it also provides
Really thorough interface documentation so as I mentioned before we have command line and Python
interfaces both of those interfaces generated from the same code
So they should be pretty much identical
It just depending how you use command line or Python it will be different
But otherwise all the options all the commands
They look exactly the same and in command line reference
You could find all the documentation for all the commands you could use it that I have some popular ones in my case
Right where I went before and it provides documentation what those and of course there is
notes for power users and quite elaborate
documentation here about all the options which are available
in those commands
Ok so let's go back to features and
First of the demos which I want to show you will be about data discovery
That's any other demo on the website and is provided with
screencast which shows all
necessary commands to carry out the
Presentation, but also provides you with
comments describing the purpose of the actions taken
moreover
You could obtain the full script for the demo so you could run it as case on your hardware
By clicking underneath the screen screencast but
For this demonstration. I'll do it interactively in a shell together with you
So
Let's get started!
If as you remember
We aggregate a lot of metadata in DataLad to provide efficient search mechanisms
In this example we'll imagine that we were looking for a data set which mentions
Raiders in his word after being associated with movie Raiders of the Lost Ark and during imaging
So we'll use datalad -search command where we'll
Just state it right, so we'll call datalad -search
Raiders neuroimaging as with a mini or all commands in DataLad
They are composed by calling datalad
then typing the command you want to implement right and then you could ask for help for that command
Which
provides you with
associated help and
On my screen took a little bit longer just because of video recording usually it's a little bit faster like
five times and
Then you actually type the parameters for this command. For search
It's actually search terms, and I'll present a few other options later on
whenever you
Start this command for the first time it will ask you to install our super data set
Under your home DataLad, in my case that slash demo is the home directory so it asks either
We want to install that super dates which you saw available on DataLad.org
in your home directory.
And that's what it's doing so it quickly installed it because it's just a small git repository without any of those data sets
Directly in a part of it, but they are linked to it as sub modules. It was really fast, and then it loads and caches
metadata, which became available in that dataset and that takes few seconds
Whenever that is done it you see that by default it just returns the paths or names of the
Datasets as they are within the hierarchy of our super dataset and
Search searches within the
Repository data set you are in so if next time
I am just running the same command it will ask me instead of: "Oh, do you want to install it?" it'll ask me either
I want to search in this super dataset which I installed in my home directory
Type yes
And it provides the same result so to avoid such interactive questions
you could explicitly mention which data set you want to search in.
In our case it will be, I'll just specify
That data set will be this
canonical
DataLad data set which is installed in your
DataLad directory when you specify it like this
It assumes location in your home directory when you use triple slashes resource identifier as the source for URLs
To install data sets then it will go to the datasets.datalad.org. And this time we'll search not for Raiders
neuroimaging, but we'll search for Haxby, one of the authors within this data set
So -s stands for the fields which we want to search through and -R will report now
Not just the path to the data set but also
list the fields which match the
Query which we ran. So in this case it should search for data sets and report the field "author".
And only the data sets where Haxby was one of the authors.
So here they are
For convenience, let's just switch to that directory
under our home
Let me clear the screen and go to that directory
So now we don't have to specify
Location of the data set explicitly, and we could just type the same query without -d and it will provide the same results
Instead of listing all matching fields, let's say in our case it was "author" field, we could
Explicitly specify which fields you want to search through or to report.
So in this case, I want to see what's the name of the dataset and what is the author of the dataset?
It's already the author, but with didn't see the name.
And you're on the command to get the output with those fields included
Well enough of searching
Let's clear the screen and what we could do now we found
The data sets right it seems to be that the list of data sets which we found
is good to be installed and we could just
rely on a paradigm of Linux where you compose commands together through by using pipe command.
So, what this magic would do?
If we didn't have these which already what happens right so we get only the list of data sets or past
Those which are not installed yet, and so OpenfMRI directory is still empty so we get the list of data sets
But then instead of manually going and doing:
"datalad install openfmri/ds00233"...
Or doing copy-paste, we could just say that result of this command
should be passed as
Arguments to the next command which will be "datalad install".
"datalad install" command installs those data sets which are either specified by the
path within current data set or you could provide URLs to
Install command and it will go to those websites and download them explicitly from there.
"datalad install" could be used with other resources
beyond our canonical DataLad distribution.
So let's run this command
as a result of it you'll see that now it goes online and
Installs all those data sets or git/git-annex repositories without any data yet
So only the files which are committed directly into git will be present.
And now we could explore what actually we have got here.
I'll use another DataLad command. Let me clear the screen to bring it on top of the screen.
Next command is "ls", which just lists
either data sets or it could be used also at list S3 URLs.
If you are interested to see what is available in S3 bucket.
And we are specifying the options: capital -L for long listing, and -r recursively
So it will go through all data sets locally in current directory.
(That's why there is a period). And then we'll just remove a list in our data sets
which are not installed because they are not of our interest here.
As you can see all those datasets, which we initially searched for and found
Right?
They became installed, so they became available on our
Local file system and "ls" gives us idea. What kind of repository it is
It's Git versus annex, which branch it is in...
What was the date of the last commit?
Also, the sizes what it tells here that we have a lot of 4 gigabytes of data referenced in this data set at the current
version we've got only 0 bytes locally installed.
We installed only those symlinks I was talking about.
So, now we could actually explore what have you got?
Some of the files that were committed directly into Git, so they became available on the file system as is
But data files we could obtain now using the "datalad get" command.
So what this command will do... Let me clear the screen again...
So you're saying: "Obtain those files! Do it in four parallel processes."
All the files which match these Shell globe expressions,
so all the data sets locally which we have
For all the subjects underneath and anatomical directory, right? We obtained all ready two OpenfMRI dataset
And now we just want to obtain those data files
Let's actually see what this one is pointing to... It points to all those data files.
And if only listed with long listing,
we'll see that those were symlinks which are actually at the moment not even present on that
Point into the files which we don't have locally and that's what git-annex would do for us
It would go online and fetch all those files
from wherever they are available
So let me run this command now
As you can see the are four processes going on
And the end.
All DataLad commands they provide you a summary of what actions did it take?
Here you could see that it got all those files ready to get okay
Or it might say get failed if it failed to get them and then provides action summary, which we might see later in other demos
So let's now run the same command which you ran before to see how much of data we actually got?
As you can see all those which we didn't ask for any data
They still keep zero bytes although all
the files that are available and we could browse them,
but those where we requested additional data files to be obtained finally list how much data
we have in the working tree
of those data sets.
That would complete the demo for "search" and "install".
Now it's your turn to find some interesting for you data sets and get the data for them
Now that we went through one of the demos on our website or we call it features which was data discovery
You could go and visit other
features described on this page. First one is for data consumers
which describes how you could generate native DataLad datasets from the website or
S3 buckets using our crawler so
If you know some resource you could create your own
DataLad crawler to obtain that data into DataLad dataset and keep it up to date with periodic reruns.
Data sharing demo will later show
examples of how you could share the data either on Github, through the github while depositing data to your website,
how I demonstrated earlier, or just for collaboration through SSH servers.
For Git and git-annex users
We give a little example of unique features present in DataLad contrasting it with
regular Git and git-annex usage.
This table outlines there those features.
We operate on multiple data sets at the same time, we operate across data sets seamlessly
So you don't have to switch directories to just operate in with specific data files they provide metadata support
And aggregate from different panel data sources and in unified authentication interface.
Also, one of the
new unique features in DataLad is ability to rerun previously ran commands on the data to see how
things changed or just keep nice
Protocol of actions you have done and record them within your git/git-annex history.
And the last one goes in detail in example on how to use HeuDiCon with your data sets and
relying on our
naming convention for how to name scanning sequences in the scanner.
I hope that you liked this presentation
and you liked what DataLad has to offer so I just want to summarize what DataLad does.
And what it does? It helps to manage and share
Available and your own data by a simple command line of Python interface.
We provide already access to over 10 terabytes of neuroimaging data
And we help with authentication, crawling of the websites, getting data from the archives in which it was originally distributed
publishing new or derived data.
Underneath we use regular pure Git and git-annex repository so whatever tools
You've got used to use you could still use them
And if you're an expert git and git-annex user
We will not limit your powers
You could do the same stuff what you did before with your key tanga tanga suppositories, so we also provide somewhat human
accessible
Metadata interface so in general if you want just to search for some datasets, it's quite convenient with datalad -search.
Documentation is growing
You're welcome to contribute, the project is open source.
I hope that after you've seen the presentation you will agree that managing data can be as simple as manage encode and software. Thank you!